{"tossups": [{"question": "An expedition from this colony used the<em> Good Hope</em> in a futile expedition to reclaim a fur trading post on the Penobscot River. Much of the congregation of John Robinson immigrated to this colony from Leiden in the Netherlands. Myles Standish was a military leader of this colony, which was governed for nearly 30 years by William Bradford. Colonists from the<em> Mayflower</em> established, for ten points, what colony near a namesake rock in Massachusetts?", "answer": "<b> Plymouth</b> Colony", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. Thomas Aquinas cited Genesis 1:28 [chapter 1, verse 28] as Biblical justification for this general action, so long as it was used as a means to divine happiness. The \u201cspoilage\u201d and \u201cenough and as good\u201d provisions limit the right to this practice, according to John Locke, who stated that this practice became legitimate through the mixing of labor. Rousseau\u2019s<em> Discourse on Inequality</em> blames all the world\u2019s \u201ccrimes, wars, and murders\u201d on this practice, which takes place through enclosure of the commons. For ten points, name this practice that Locke sought to protect alongside life and liberty.", "answer": "<b> own</b>ing private<b> property</b> (accept equivalents; accept descriptions relating to<b> buy</b>ing <b>property</b>; accept<b> land</b>,<b> good</b>s,<b> thing</b>s, etc. as substitutes for property; accept the<b> pursuit of property </b>and similar phrases after \u201cspoilage\u201d is read; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "One ruler of this country, Fasilides, established a new capital at the city of Gondar. The Jesuit Pedro P\u00b4aez wrote a two volume history of this country, where the Oromo people migrated from south to north in the 16th century. This country is home to churches cut into the rock near the town of Lalibela. This country was ruled by members of the Solomonic Dynasty, like Zara Yaqob. For ten points, name this modern African country whose land was once ruled by the Kingdom of Axum on the Horn of Africa.", "answer": "<b> Ethiopia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this European country that committed racial discrimination in Caribbean colonies like Jamaica and Barbados.", "answer": "<b> U</b>nited<b> K</b>ingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland (accept Great<b> Britain</b>; accept <b>England</b>) (5) In 1886, Herman Presser and his group Lehr und Wehr Verein cited this amendment to challenge an Illinois law. This amendment\u2019s jurisprudence favored the collective rights interpretation established in <em>US v. Miller</em> until the Roberts Court recently applied the individual rights doctrine in<em> DC v. Heller</em> and <em>McDonald v. Chicago</em>. For ten points, name this amendment that mentions a \u201cwell-regulated militia\u201d and guarantees the right to bear arms. ANSWER:<b> 2</b>nd Amendment to the U.S. Constitution", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This foodstuff was first made from a plant called teosinte [tay-oh-sin-tay]. In 1885, Charles Cretors invented a machine to make this foodstuff, which he displayed at the 1893 Chicago World\u2019s Fair. During World War II, sugar rations led to the tripling in consumption of this good, which the Redenbacher family started selling during the Great Depression. For ten points, name this food, a sweetened variety of which is found with peanuts in Cracker Jack, and which is the highest-selling food in American movie theaters.", "answer": "<b> popcorn</b> (prompt on corn)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A primary source about life in this empire is provided by the letters of Lady Mary Wortley Montagu. The murdered miniaturist Elegant Effendi works under this empire in Orhan Pamuk\u2019s novel<em> My Name</em> <em>is Red</em>. Cervantes\u2019s left hand was badly maimed while fighting against this empire as part of the Spanish contingent at the Battle of Lepanto. For ten points, name this empire where authors were patronized by nobles in 19th century Bursa and Istanbul.", "answer": "<b> Ottoman</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s most famous oration notes that \u201cit is the young men who say yes or no\u201d since \u201cLooking Glass is dead.\u201d This man, who allied with a small group from the Palouse tribe, was captured after a broken truce at the Battle of Bear Paw Mountain. This man declared that \u201cmy heart is sick and sad\u201dand \u201cI will fight no more forever\u201d after his tribe was stopped by troops just miles south of the northern border. For ten points, name this chief of the Nez Perce who tried to lead his people to Canada.", "answer": "Chief<b> Joseph</b> (or<b> Hin-mah-too-yah-lat-kekt</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This city includes the Vila Amaury attraction, an underwater village submerged in the artificial Lake Paranoa. Construction on this city began as the result of the \u201cfifty years of progress in five\u201d plan under Juscelino Kubitschek. It was built to take on the shape of an airplane by Lucio Costa. Oscar Niemeyer was commissioned to design this city as its government sought to move to a more central location from Rio de Janeiro. For ten points, name the capital of Brazil.", "answer": "<b> Brasilia</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "Legends about this site hold that it was originally built for Precha Ket Mealea. An early visitor to this site, Zhou Daguan, wrote that it was built in one night by a divine hand. This site features a mural of 92 asuras and 88 devas using the serpent Vasuki to churn the Sea of Milk. Though it was first built to honor Vishnu by Suryavarman II, this site was later rededicated to become a Buddhist place of worship. For ten points, name this temple complex constructed by the Khmer empire, a national symbol on the Cambodian flag.", "answer": "<b> Angkor Wat</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "This process led to the martyring of the Bandiera Brothers. The Battle of Solferino helped accelerate this process by forcing Austria to cede land in the Treaty of Z\u00a8urich. This process spread to the southern regions with the Expedition of the Thousand. Count Cavour helped engineer this process alongside Giuseppe Garibaldi. For ten points, name this process which resulted in a new nation centered at Rome.", "answer": "<b> Italian unification</b> (accept the<b> Risorgimento</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "At this battle\u2019s conclusion, William Washington had his horse shot out from under him as he tried to pursue the enemy commander. This battle\u2019s losing side was misled into fighting by a report of an imminent attack on Fort Ninety-Six. The winning side in this battle deployed three defensive lines by the Broad River and resisted multiple assaults by the British Legion, leading Daniel Morgan\u2019s men to eventually rout Banastre Tarleton\u2019s forces. For ten points, name this 1781 battle of the Carolinas campaign that was fought on cattle grazing ground.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Cowpens</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This nation achieved recognition in the Twelve Years\u2019 Truce, which was eventually broken when this nation was attacked by the Duke of Olivares. The Council of Blood was set up to quell insurrections in this nation by the Duke of Alba, who had been deployed by Philip II. The Peace of Westphalia formally ended this nation\u2019s Eighty Years\u2019 War with Spain and granted it its independence. For ten points, name this Low Country whose independence struggle was led by the House of Orange.", "answer": "The<b> Netherlands</b> (or<b> Holland</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A group of artists from this country known as \u201cLos grande tres\u201d [los grand-ay trace] were commissioned for murals in public buildings by Minister of Education Jos\u00b4e Vasconcelos. Jos\u00b4e Posada\u2019s prints made in this country often feature<em> calaveras</em> or skeletons. Another artist from this country sparked outrage by including a portrait of Vladimir Lenin in his<em> Man at the Crossroads</em>. For ten points, name this country home to muralist Diego Rivera and his wife, Frida Kahlo.", "answer": "<b> Mexico</b> (or the<b> United Mexican States</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In 1956, the leader of this organization wrote an open letter claiming that T.R.M. Howard\u2019s \u201cfalse charges\u201d were \u201ca disservice to common decency.\u201d In 1971, a \u201cCitizens\u2019Commission\u201d used the broadcast of the Ali-Frazier \u201cFight of the Century\u201d as a distraction to successfully raid one of this organization\u2019s (+) suburban offices in Media, Pennsylvania. That burglary recovered documents used by the Church Committee to declassify this organization\u2019s (*) </b> COINTELPRO project, which illegally targeted activists like Martin Luther King, Jr. with illegal surveillance. For ten points, name this American law enforcement agency that was led for nearly 5 decades by J. Edgar Hoover.", "answer": "<b> Federal Bureau of Investigation</b> (or<b> FBI</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Thomas Aquinas\u2019s \u201cPange lingua\u201d forms the basis of one of these pieces by Josquin des Prez [joh-skan dez prezz]. One of these compositions includes material originally written for the death of Augustus II and accession of Augustus III of Poland, and unusually calls one</b> <b>movement (+)</b> <b>\u201cSymbolum Nicenum.\u201d Another of these works supposedly convinced the</b> <b>\u201cSymbolum Nicenum.\u201d Another of these works supposedly convinced the</b> <b>Council of Trent to not ban polyphony and was written for Pope (*)</b> <b>Council of Trent to not ban polyphony and was written for Pope (*)</b> Marcellus by Giovanni Palestrina. J.S. Bach wrote a B minor example of, for ten points, what type of sacred musical work that includes Credo and Kyrie movements and sets the weekly Catholic liturgy?", "answer": "<b> mass</b>es (do not accept requiem mass)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "After already spending 2 billion dollars, the development of one of these facilities named the SSC was canceled by (+) Congress in 1993. Public safety concerns were raised after people thought one of these facilities built by CERN was capable of producing black (*)</b> holes. The Tevatron and the RHIC are examples of, for ten points, what scientific devices used to study physics at the atomic level, such as the Large Hadron Collider?", "answer": "<b> particle accelerator</b>s (prompt on \u201catom-smasher\u201d and other colloquial terms for a thing that bashes particles together and/or makes them go really fast)", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "<b>This man created a branch of philosophy inspired by Jan Jakob Maria de Groot called Universism. During the Great Depression, this defense minister sent troops to break the Menstad conflict, and as prime minister, he created the (+) Hirden paramilitary. Following the German invasion of his country in Operation Weser Exercise, this man launched a coup via radio broadcast. This man was executed in (*)</b> Akershus Fortress in 1945 after he collaborated with the SS in the Holocaust. The Nasjonal Samling party was led by, for ten points, what infamous Norwegian traitor?", "answer": "Vidkun<b> Quisling</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Participants in this event were declared to be not culpable in a trial stemming from Plenty Horses\u2019 assassination of Edward Casey. The day after this event, James Forsyth was attacked in the Bloody Pocket during the (+) Drexel Mission Fight. This event, which took place on the Pine Ridge reservation, was partly a reaction to fears that Wovoka\u2019s (*)</b> Ghost Dance movement might be a signal for an attack, though its immediate cause was Black Coyote\u2019s refusal to hand over his rifle. For ten points, name this 1890 event in which more than 100 members of the Lakota tribe were massacred.", "answer": "<b> Wounded Knee</b> massacre", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Due to anti-Semitism, one leader of this country changed his last name from Kohn before assuming power. Despite not having a navy, this country was ruled during</b> <b>the interwar period by an admiral who accommodated the fascist (+)</b> <b>Arrow Cross</b> <b>Party. Following World War I, this country underwent a brief period of Communist government under (*) </b> Bela Kun. For ten points, name this country that lost Slovakia and Transylvania after World War I, but kept the region around its capital of Budapest.", "answer": "<b> Hungary</b> (accept<b> Magyarorszag</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}